Oscar Umana

Software Developer

Toronto, Ontario oscarumana1021@gmail.com | 647-673-2964 https://github.com/oscaru21

I am a highly motivated and data-driven software developer with experience in developing and testing software applications. I possess excellent problem-solving and communication skills. I am fluent in English, Spanish and French which allows me to collaborate with diverse teams. I am very passionate for machine learning and data science.

EXPERIENCE

Centennial College - Student Researcher; Toronto

Jan 2023 – Present

- Analyzed production optimization strategies and conducted research on Linux machines automation, the proposed solution helped parallelized multiple processes and reduce the average time by 50%.
- Developed Python scripts and unit tests that streamlined and automated various Linux processes, eliminating all manual intervention for device initial configuration.
- Synthesized findings into a comprehensive report and presented recommendations to the team.

Centennial College - Math Tutor; Toronto

Jan 2023 – Present

- Provided one-on-one tutoring for college students in courses including Calculus, Linear Algebra and Statistics.
- Utilized active learning techniques such as problem-based learning, real-life examples, and Data visualizations
 with Python and Matplotlib to engage students and facilitate their understanding.

Telus - Software Developer Intern; San Salvador

Jan 2022 – Jun 2022

- Documented object-oriented database entities with UML class diagrams and recorded learning material which helped new hires learn the internal processes faster.
- Optimized SQL queries, reducing query execution time by 30% and improving the overall performance of the database-driven applications, using techniques such as indexing and reducing data redundancy.
- Participated in the whole software development life cycle having exposure to technologies like Java, JavaScript, React.js, HTML, CSS, Junit, Git, Jenkins, and Google Cloud.

EDUCATION

Centennial College – Software Technology and Artificial Intelligence Advance Diploma

GPA: 4.28/4.5 (A+)

2022 - 2024

Relevant Courses: Testing & QA, Web App Development, Linear Algebra & Statistics, Algorithms & Data Structures, Java Programming, Supervised Learning, Networking for Developers, Advance Database Concepts, Software Systems Design

Don Bosco University - Bachelor of Engineering in Electronics

GPA: 8.5/10 (Cum laude)

2016 - 2021

Relevant Courses: C# Programming, Statistics, Microprocessors, Digital Electronics, Project Management, Computer Architecture.

SKILLS

Python, Java, Software Development, JavaScript, C++, CSS, HTML, SQL, React.js, Git, Node.js, Web Development, Machine Learning, Data Science, Data Analysis, NumPy, Matplotlib, Pandas, PyTorch, NLP, Docker, Jira, Junit, PyTest, Unit testing, Test Automation.